Guide to the Edward FitzGerald Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Edward FitzGerald collection
1863-1883
GEN MSS 235
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.25
(1 box)
Includes commonplace book of FitzGerald; letters from FitzGerald to Herman Biddell (1863-81), Joseph Fletcher, Francis Hindes Groome, Robert Hindes Groome, Mssrs Smith and Elder, and four unidentified recipients.
FitzGerald, Edward, 1809-1883
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of materials pertaining to Edward Fitzgerald.
Commonplace books; Biddell, Herman; FitzGerald, Edward, 1809-1883; Fletcher, Joseph; Groome, Francis Hindes, 1851-1902; Groome, Robert Hindes, 1810-1889; Smith, Elder, and Co
- Letters from FitzGerald, 1863-[81]
  - 22 ALS to Herman Biddell, Woodbridge, 1863-[81] (Box 1, Folder +)
    Scope and Contents
    Accompanied by carbon typescripts. Twelve of the letters are printed in Edward FitzGerald's Letters and Literary Remains, edited by William Aldis Wright, London, 1902-03. 7 vols.
  - ALS to "Posh" [Joseph Fletcher], Woodbridge, [1867?] Jun 8 (Box 1, Folder +)
    Signed "Robertina Jacobs."
  - ALS to "Posh" [Joseph Fletcher], [n.p.], n.d. (Box 1)
    Signed "FitzGerald, Fletcher, & co."
  - 2 AL, signed with initials, to Francis Groome, Woodbridge, [n.y.] Jun 24, Jul 2 (Box 1, Folder +)
  - ALS to [Robert Hindes] Groome, Lowestoft, 1866 Dec 2 (Box 1, Folder +)
    Printed in Francis Hindes Groome's Two Suffolk Friends, Edinburgh, 1894, p. 72-73.
  - ALS to Messrs Smith and Elder, Woodbridge, 1877 Oct 30 (Box 1, Folder +)
    With envelope.
  - 3 AL, signed with initials, to unidentified recipients, Lowestoft, [n.y.] Dec 26, [n.y.] Wed, 1866 Apr 3 (Box 1, Folder +)
  - ALS proposing a new edition of Selden's Table Talk be brought out, [1846] (Box 1, Folder +)
- Writings, n.d.
  - Commonplace Book, n.d. (Box 1, Folder +)
    Autograph manuscript. Folios 1, 23, and 60, with about 10 others at end of manuscript (probably blank), have been cut out. Many leaves are written on both sides. FitzGerald's autograph pasted on fly-leaf. Accompanied by TLS from W. R. Browne to Thomas B. Mosher, TLS from Ralph A. Beals to Mr. Otis Bradley, and 2 periodical articles, all concerning the manuscript.